

# Alexandre Chapiro

I am interested in applied perception and psychophysics as related to computational display, as well as image and video processing techniques. In particular, I've worked on topics in stereo 3D, high dynamic range, brightness and color, frame rate and motion, user experience and virtual reality.

## Professional Experience

2018-now Apple Inc., Cupertino

Senior Display Help identify and cultivate new display and image processing technologies and

Engineer experiences for future Apple products

affiliation Core Display Incubation Team, managed by Nicolas Bonnier

2017-2018 Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale

Senior Conducted research and obtained experimental results on human perception factors

Researcher relevant to business needs

affiliation Applied Vision Science group, managed by Robin Atkins

2011-2016 Disney Research, Zurich

Researcher Conducted research on novel displays, stereo 3D, high dynamic range, high framerate

and human perception resulting in four patent applications and several publications

affiliation Stereo and Displays group, managed by Aljoša Smolić

## Education

#### 2011-2015 **PhD in Computer Science**

institution Federal Institute of Technology Zurich (ETHZ), Zurich, Switzerland

thesis title Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays

affiliation Computer Graphics Laboratory

supervisors Prof. Markus Gross. Co-Advisor: Dr. Aljoša Smolić

2010-2011 Masters' Degree in Applied Mathematics

institution Institute of Pure and Applied Mathematics (IMPA), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

thesis title Improving Mobile Video

affiliation Visgraf laboratory

supervisors Prof. Paulo Cezar Pinto Carvalho. Co-Advisor: Prof. Luiz Velho

2007–2009 <b>U</b>	ndergraduate	Degree in	Mathematics

- institution Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF), Juiz de Fora, Brazil
- thesis title An Introduction to Degree Theory
- affiliation Computer Graphics Laboratory
- supervisors Prof. Luiz Faria, Marcelo Bernardes Vieira
- 2016-2016 Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale
  - Intern Conducted research on the human visual system guided by business unit needs
- affiliation Applied Vision Science group, managed by Robin Atkins

## Teaching

- Feb.2014 **Teaching assistant**, Math. Foundations of Computer Graphics and Vision, ETHZ.
- to Jun.2014 Graduate class teaching mathematical techniques in visual computing
  - Feb.2015 **Teaching assistant**, Math. Foundations of Computer Graphics and Vision, ETHZ.
- to Jun.2015
  - Feb.2012 **Teaching assistant**, *Informatik 1*, ETHZ.
- to Jun.2012 Undergradute class teaching fundaments of informatics to engineering students
  - Feb.2013 **Teaching assistant**, *Informatik 1*, ETHZ.
- to Jun.2013

## Academic Honors

- 2015 Second youngest PhD to graduate from the CS department at ETH Zurich at 25
- 2011 Finished 2-year Master's program at the National Institute of Pure and Applied Mathematics in 18 months
- 2009 Finished 4-year undergraduate program in Mathematics at the Federal University of Juiz de Fora in 3 years with the highest GPA in the graduating class
- 2007 Ranked 1st in admission examinations, Federal University of Juiz de Fora
- 2006 Gold Medalist, Brazilian Astronomy Olympiad
- 2006 Gold Medalist, Brazilian Mathematics Olympiad for Public School Students. 95th place among approximately 5.3 million students
- 2005 Gold Medalist, Brazilian Mathematics Olympiad for Public School Students. 9th place among approximately 3.8 million students

## Academic Service

- Committee 2018, SIBGRAPI International Program Committee.
- Reviewing 2018, SIBGRAPI, Eurographics.
  - 2017, SIGGRAPH, Pacific Graphics, IEEE TIP.
  - 2016, SIGGRAPH Asia, Graphics Interface, IEEE TIP, JOSA.
  - 2015, SIGGRAPH, SIGGRAPH Asia, ICIP, IEEE CG&A, IEEE TVCG.
  - 2014, Pacific Graphics, CG Forum.
  - 2012, 3DV.
  - **L** +1 (650) 770 6470 ☑ alex@chapiro.net ② chapiro.net in alexandre-chapiro-a8342520

## Awards and Funding

Oct.2011 Participant, European Commission Program FP7.

to Oct.2013

Mar.2010 Awarded, Master program fellowship, CNPq.

to Jul.2011

Jan.2009 Awarded, Undergraduate research scholarship, FAPEMIG.

to Dec.2009

Jan.2008 Awarded, Undergraduate research scholarship, CNPq.

to Dec.2008

Mar.2007 Awarded, Scholarship for winners OBMEP 2006 mathematics olympics, CNPq.

to Jan.2008

Mar.2006 Awarded, Scholarship for winners OBMEP 2005 mathematics olympics, CNPq.

to Jan.2007

Jan.2005 Awarded, High-school research scholarship, CNPq.

to Dec.2005

 Obs.: CNPq is the Brazilian national funding agency. FAPEMIG is the funding agency for the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil

## Invited Talks and Presentations

invited talk: Cinematic Motion.

NAB show 2018, Las Vegas, invited by Jaclyn Pytlarz

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

IBM 2017, Rio de Janeiro, hosted by Emilio Vital Brazil

invited talk: Computer Graphics, (popular lecture).

IF Sudeste MG 2017, Juiz de Fora, hosted by Elena Konstantinova

invited talk: Computer Graphics, (popular lecture).

IF Sudeste MG 2016, Rio Pomba, hosted by Lucas Lattari

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

Dolby Laboratories 2016, Sunnyvale, hosted by Timo Kunkel

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

Technicolor 2015, Rennes, hosted by Erik Reinhard

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for 3D Displays.

Max Planck Institut 2015, Saarbrucken, hosted by Piotr Didyk

paper talk: Stereo from Shading.

EGSR 2015

paper talk: Perceptual Evaluation of Cardboarding in 3D Content Visualization.

SAP 2015

paper talk: Optimizing Stereo-to-Multiview Conv. for Autostereo. Displays.

Eurographics 2015

## Languages

Portuguese Fluent Native speaker
Russian Fluent Native speaker

English Fluent TOEFL iBT 117/120, Cambridge FCE and CAE exams with A grades

Spanish Fluent 3 years of school in Spain

French Advanced Alliance Française DELF diplome - 2005

German Beginner Approximately A2 level

## References

#### Prof. Dr. Markus Gross.

Director of Disney Research Zurich. Full Professor, ETH Zurich.

## Prof. Dr. Aljoša Smolić,

SFI Research Professor of Creative Technologies, Trinity College Dublin.

## Scott Daly,

Senior Memeber of Science Staff, Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale.

## Dr. Tunç Aydın,

Research Scientist, Disney Research Zurich.

## Publications

## **Papers**

## Influence of Screen Size and Field of View on Perceived Brightness,

ACM Transactions on Applied Perception (TAP), 2018,

Chapiro, A., Kunkel, T., Atkins, R., Daly, S.

## Unfolding the 8-bit Era,

European Conference on Visual Media Production 2015,

Zund, F., Berard, P., Chapiro, A., Schmid, S., Ryffel, A., Bermano, A., Gross, M., Sumner, R.

## Art-Directable Continuous Dynamic Range Video,

Compters & Graphics, Elsevier, 2015,

Chapiro, A., Aydin, T., Stefanoski, N., Croci, S., Smolic, A., Gross, M.

## Video Content and Structure Description Based on Keyframes, Clusters and Storyboards,

IEEE International Workshop on Multimedia Signal Processing, Xiamen-China, 2015,

Junyent, M., Beltran, P., Farre, M., Pont-Tuset, J., Chapiro, A., Smolic, A.

#### Stereo from Shading,

Eurographics Symposium on Rendering, Darmstadt-Germany, 2015. (E&I track), Chapiro, A., O'Sullivan, C., Jarosz, W., Gross, M., Smolic, A.

## Perceptual Evaluation of Cardboarding in 3D Content Visualization,

ACM Symposium on Applied Perception, Vancouver-Canada, 2014. (Short paper), Chapiro, A., Diamanti, O., Poulakos, S., O'Sullivan, C., Smolic, A., Gross, M.

## Optimizing Stereo-to-Multiview Conversion for Autostereoscopic Displays,

Eurographics, Strasbourg-France, 2014,

Chapiro, A., Heinzle, S., Aydin, T., Poulakos, S., Zwicker, M., Smolic, A., Gross, M.

## Towards Mobile HDR Video,

Eurographics, Llandudno-UK, 2011. (Extended abstract) Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Cicconet, M., Velho, L.

## **Detection of High Frequency Regions in Multiresolution,**

International Conference on Image Processing, Cairo-Egypt, 2009. Mota, V.F., Perez, E.A., Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Vieira, M.B.

## High Frequency Assessment from Multiresolution Analysis,

International Conference on Computational Science, Baton Rouge-USA, 2009 Castro, T.K., Perez, E. A., Mota, V. F., Chapiro, A., Vieira, M. B., Freire, W. P.

#### **Patents**

## Systems and methods for automatic key frame extraction and storyboard interface generation for video,

US Patent US9552520 B1, 2017 (Related to our 2015 paper) Smolic, A., Martin, M., Pont-Tuset, J., Chapiro, A., Guiu, M.

## Methods for creating and distributing art-directable continuous dynamic range video,

US20160353164 A1, 2016 (Related to our 2015 paper)

Smolic, A., Chapiro, A., Croci, S., Aydin, T., Stefanoski, N., Gross, M.

## Visual salience of online video as a predictor of success,

US20170061235 A1, 2015 (Related to our 2015 poster)

Frey, S., Accardo, AM., Sumner, R., Huber, R., Chapiro, A.

## Depth modification for display applications,

US20150348273 A1, 2015 (Related to our 2014 paper)

Chapiro, A., Aydin, T., Poulakos, S., Heinzle, S., Smolic, A.

## **Book Chapters**

## Discrete Wavelets on Edges,

InTech open publisher, 2011

Chapiro, A., Knop, T., Mota, V., Perez, E., Bernardes, M., Freire W. P.

#### **Posters**

## The Influence of Visual Salience on Video Consumption Behavior A Survival Analysis Approach,

ACM Web Science, Oxford-United Kingdom, 2015 Huber, R., Scheibehenne, B., Chapiro, A., Frey, S., Sumner, R.

## Filter Based Deghosting for Exposure Fusion Video,

SIGGRAPH, Vancouver-Canada, 2011. Student Research Competition Semi-Finalist Chapiro, A., Cicconet, M., Velho, L.

## Towards Mobile HDR Video,

International Conference on Computational Photography, Pittsburg-USA, 2011 Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Cicconet, M., Velho, L.

## Mountain's Pass Theorem,

Minas-Gerais Meeting of Partial Diferential Equations, Itajuba-Brazil, 2009 Chapiro, A., Pereira, F.

## Other

#### Image Domain Warping for Advanced 3D Video Applications,

IEEE COMSOC MMTC E - Letter, 2014. (Invited letter)

Smolic A., Wang, O., Lang, M., Stefanoski, N., Farre, M., Greisen, P., Heinzle, S., Schaffner, M., Chapiro, A., Sorkine-Hornung, A., Gross, M.

## Computational Photography,

IMPA, Rio de Janeiro-Brazil, 2011. (Technical report) Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Velho, L.